so hi my name is Joe brewer and in this
presentation I want to share with you a
powerful framework that can be used to
help think about large scale social
change efforts and that is the framework
of cultural scaffolding and we're going
to discuss this in the context of the
efforts that are needed to make the
transition to global sustainability now
first off to really get a sense of what
I mean by scaffolding we're all familiar
with the use of scaffolding and
construction where the basic frame of a
building isn't yet able to support
itself and so the scaffolding is set up
to help the construction workers to
build the basic supports that then
enable the building to stand on its own
and the scaffolding at that point can be
removed so you can think of scaffolding
is something that supports a
developmental process but that doesn't
necessarily need to continue to function
or serve an active role at a later stage
in the development now when we think
about this in the context of culture
it's really helpful to think of
scaffolding in the way that we raise
children
so just reflect for a moment on how much
support is needed to take someone from
being a newborn all the way through
adolescence where they have a supportive
environment where there are people who
give them objects to play with that
teach them basic skills and knowledge
and over time they build on these things
to be able to develop as a person so in
the same way that all of the scaffolding
is provided to raise a child into early
adulthood we can think about larger
cultural patterns as building upon a
number of supports as a process develops
and changes that are vital to the future
possibilities or future capabilities
that that culture is is eventually going
to have now before we go into cultural
scaffolding in detail I want to take a
brief detour into the world of
thermodynamics and talk about entropy
now entropy is the
of disorder within a system as you can
see what these well-organized horizontal
and vertical rows of dots in the left
the low entropy picture then in this
kind of a system that has that kind of
uniformity it doesn't require very much
information to describe everything
that's going on whereas the same number
of dots in the right hand picture where
it says high entropy requires more
information to to reproduce that pattern
and so there's a higher level of
information that's involved so sometimes
this is called having more disorder in
the system but you can also think of it
as how much information does it take to
characterize it now the image on the
bottom is a fractal called the
sierpinski triangle and what I want you
to see is that as as you go through the
steps of removing pieces from a triangle
in a very specific way the amount of
entropy goes up so there's a way of
thinking about patterns that simply by
playing out the pattern you can increase
the amount of disorder or the amount of
structure in a system well we can think
in the same way about how culture can
have increasing structure over time as
its increasing its entropy and the key
thing is that there's the second law of
thermodynamics which says that in any
kind of energy exchange entropy can
never reduce so this is a physical limit
on our ability to organize information
that anytime we do work on a system we
either keep the amount of information
the same or we increase it so we can't
reduce it so that means that the
scaffolding process for energy exchanges
in thermodynamics is always one that's
leaning toward greater empathy over to
our greater entropy over time and a
simple way to think about this is if you
are to take this course this wine glass
goblet and shatter it as you can see
that as time goes on as its breaking
down its energy is being used up as it
breaks but you would have to do a lot of
work and add energy and very specific
way
is to move these broken pieces back
together and reproduce the original
goblet this in thermodynamics is called
irreversibility and a process where
entropy increases is also one that is
irreversible which means that it doesn't
spontaneously go back to the pattern
that existed before but instead work has
to be done and in some cases it's in
practical terms impossible to do the
work to return to the original state so
you can think of this process of going
irreversibly from one organization of a
system to some higher level disorder or
higher entropy state of a system as
being something that is there reversible
is that's a constraint on how patterns
form in nature in general so when we
look at something like this mold that is
forming in a petri dish you can see that
in the beginning there's very little
structure and then as it grows it
creates new structures as it goes along
as it's radiating outward and this is
not violating the laws of thermodynamics
actually we can see that the amount of
organizational structure is increasing
over time but also we can see that the
patterns that were there before or of
setting constraints for what can come
later
and this is something we can see really
well if we look at how a snowflake grows
so here is an ice crystal or what we
would call snowflake and a normal
everyday language you can see how as the
ice crystal is forming that the
structures that existed before set
constraints on what kind of structures
can emerge later so you can think of the
existing structures of this ice crystal
as being like a scaffolding on which new
structures grow and in the same way that
this ice crystal can only grow in
certain ways without violating the laws
of thermodynamics cultural scaffolding
can only develop in certain ways without
violating the laws of physics but also
some of the laws of cultural revolution
that we'll discuss a little
later on now these constraints on how
patterns form can be quite complex as
you can see here with these ma with
these mushrooms that in living systems
and biology the constraints on
development can be quite complex
so the scaffolding for earlier
structures in the development of an
organism's body can create very
elaborate structures later on so the
scaffolding process can be destructive
the way that we saw with the broken wine
glass or it can be highly generative and
create very details and intricate
structures now the way that I'm going to
be talking about cultural scaffolding
for the rest of this presentation is
informed by this paper written by
William Wimsatt and James Gray Simha
where they talk in great detail about
how an entrenchment process leads to the
kinds of scaffolded structures in
culture so if you want to learn more
about this then I'm going to talk about
here I recommend going and getting a
copy of this paper so here's how they
describe what cultural scaffolding is
they say that cultural scaffolding is
the generative interactions between
actors artifacts practices and
infrastructure so the culture is able to
build upon itself and I've clearly here
an image of a teacher who is teaching a
student how to do mathematics and you
can see that there are two actors in the
scene there's the teacher and the
student they're using artifacts in this
case the chalk and the blackboard in the
classroom that they're in and that
they're engaging in different kind of
pedagogical practices to teach the child
how to do mathematics in this case
learning basic arithmetic and that
there's a larger set of infrastructure
in the curriculum of the entire school
and larger shared knowledge in the
culture I'll say the same language that
they both speak and the infrastructure
of the classroom or the school system so
the ability to learn something like
mathematics requires these interactions
between the actors performing different
tasks the artifacts that they use the
practices that they're using to engage
in activities with the artifacts and the
structures
of their social environment it was in
the same way we could see how a parent
was teaching their child how to walk he
is providing the scaffolding every step
of the way as the child's brain and body
develops or in a more complex setting
like learning how to do ballet there is
a whole set of structured practices
where the teacher will use different
artifacts like the bar that's on the
wall that the students will put their
feet up on and do stretches and
movements and so there's quite a lot of
complexity that can arise between the
generative interactions of cultural
scaffolding and of course in the final
picture we have two people working in a
chemistry lab where you can imagine how
many years of cultural scaffolding or
formal education or needed in different
laboratory settings to learn how to be
an active professional chemist so in
every one of these cases the cultural
scaffolding is quite complex and it can
last anywhere from weeks through many
years of development across the person's
lifespan
so now returning to this idea of
cultural scaffolding as a development
process though we can see really well
for how children grow up from newborns
to adults that we can also see things
like after a certain period of time
there may be scaffolding that's already
put in place certain structures so that
other structures are much more difficult
to learn and a popular example is
learning languages there's a well-known
phenomenon that parts of the brain
develop their capacity to learn language
very well but at a very early age and
then later in life it takes much more
effort to learn the language that it
would have earlier on so we can think of
there being physical scaffolding in the
structures of the brain itself that
might hinder or help how the cultural
scaffolding process works for the
ability to learn new
offices similarly if we think of
something like differential calculus or
other kinds of advanced mathematics
where it may require learning more
elementary forms of mathematics so that
the concepts and the language and the
skills are present for doing more
advanced mathematics so we can think of
there being sequencing for some cultural
scaffolding processes that are necessary
to learn some things earlier before
other things can be learned later on so
there might be developmental constraints
in terms of sequencing as well as having
critical periods of development where
it's easier or more difficult to put
scaffolding in place and now there are
other kinds of experiences in our lives
all we can see how this cultural
scaffolding process works for example if
you've already taken a pathway in your
life where you got a degree and now have
a career but you want to go back and get
another degree and learn knowledge that
you could apply to change careers that
this is something that takes time and
effort so we can't simply add any
cultural Skype thing that we want but
sometimes the ways that we've chosen how
our lives unfold or just the way our
lives are developed without us having
any say in it may cut off the ability to
do certain things so that it's more
effortful core it's disruptive to what
we're doing to make big changes
similarly we might be financially or
legally locked and obligations such as
if you take out a mortgage on a house
and you owe money and it's difficult to
move without selling the home that
basically you have created a kind of
entrenchment for yourself where it's
much more difficult to make big changes
in your life without addressing this
this debt or this owned piece of
property that's now a part of your life
and of course with the example of
starting a family you can see how
there's an irreversibility to the kinds
of choices and priorities that people
have before having children versus after
having children
so all of these are aspects about
cultural scaffolding works where large
changes may be disruptive and be
effortful later in life or that we may
walk ourselves into pathways where it's
very difficult to change and do
something quite different because the
constraints of our choices have set us
into a path that makes development away
from that path more difficult so all of
this is about how about cultural
scaffolding constrains what can develop
in the future so not only is this true
for people's lives it's also true for
the development of technology so if you
think about as this graphic shows the
way the technology builds on itself such
as how the designs of automobiles can
build on previous designs that came
before where there may have been
weaknesses in the design where was a
vehicle that was unsafe to drive so they
made modifications to make it more safe
or they may have had new breakthrough
innovations and materials that create
more lightweight metal alloys for
example or there might be new tools and
technologies for designing the
automotive engineering design features
of the cars but there is a developmental
pathway through which previous designs
create optimal paths for developing new
designs so that through a process of
iteration you can have considerable
improvements in the technology over time
and this whole complex process depends
on cultural scaffolding every step of
the way for example you have people who
serve different roles as they develop
and design or manufacture and distribute
these automobiles such as the wine
worker doing some some welding in this
picture here and there's also quite a
lot of artifacts and infrastructure that
are used to inform how automotive
engineering gets done so there might be
robotic automation and factories there
could be the use of sketches or digital
drafting work creating blueprints but in
either case this process of creating
generative interactions between the
people of the artifacts the practices
and the infrastructure is how the
technology
develops over time and as even larger
level as we design and develop our
technologies such as the use of the
automobile we have other kinds of
interacting structures and systems that
scaffold the development as well such as
transitioning from the horse and buggy
to paved roads and highways for
automobiles which creates unintended
consequences like traffic congestion or
it changes the way that we use the land
so that we dedicate more of the land
surface to automobile transport to
moving around of the machines rather
than some alternative use of the land
such as maintaining pristine forests or
if we're using it as agriculture then
you can really see this development
process in this set of images which
shows how the structures of the land for
the location of Disneyland changed over
time as a built up and became more
complex so just as we saw with the
mushroom that was growing earlier in
that animation that we talked about
briefly a few minutes ago
you can see how there can be very
complex and intricate structures that
arise through this cultural scaffolding
process so that over time you can have
an entire city that is filled with
different relationships between people's
structures and artifacts that shape what
kinds of decisions they can make in the
future
so cultural scaffolding greatly limits
the developments that can happen in the
future but also allows for quite
sophisticated complicated and nuanced
developments to build upon what did come
before now let's take a step back and
think about this very simply using a
mental image and this image comes from
developmental biology for the way that a
fertilized egg was developed through a
childhood through adulthood stages for
any living organism where the marble at
the top of the scene as it rolls down as
it rolls downhill it falls into one path
or another and as it goes into different
paths the way that the Lance
laid out it's meant to show that if you
want to move from one channel to another
you have to do work on the ball in this
case you know pushing it back up the
hill that are pushing it over a hill
sideways and this is meant to be a
visual metaphor for how developmental
choices will lock us into some pathways
development and not others and we've
already seen several examples of that
and the way that we talked about well a
childhood development and learning
language or developing complex skills
like advanced mathematics or also in the
design of technology over time that
there is a kind of lock-in that happens
where their work has to be done to
change paths when you can already see
with the implications of this for
thinking about the global ecological
crisis which we'll get to in a moment
now here's an example where we can start
to see that the generative interactions
can be quite dynamic so here we have a
scene where the structures of the
landscape the shape of the road and
where the entrances and exits are allow
for constraints that create the patterns
of traffic flow so just as the
structures help shape what the patterns
are in real time for the movement of
traffic you can see that cultural
scaffolding can be quite dynamic for a
moment to moment and if we go up in a
level higher we can see for an entire
city that there are tremendous
constraints in an urban landscape like
this one on where traffic can flow which
ways it can flow and at what speeds it
can flow so the scaffolding for social
environments in today's world can be
very entrenched and can be multifaceted
and lead to very complex multiple level
structures like a 21st century urban
landscape so I just want you to think
for a moment as you look at images like
this one out of London just how much
cultural scaffolding has developed
throughout the 4,000 year history of the
city creating a place that is going to
be very limited and how we can change it
is already very much on a pathway with
inertia and
ability and all of its embedded
structures so what would be involved in
the cultural scaffolding process to move
away from this kind of infrastructure to
something different the same thing could
be said about large-scale agriculture
where a few flyover most parts of the
United States or Western Europe or
really just about any part of the world
that's not too high in the latitudes
you'll see that the rand works like this
where most of the ground cover has been
converted for human uses to use as
agriculture we've already transformed
the kinds of landscapes the kind of
forest ecosystems or or grassland
ecosystems that have been turned into
agriculture how much entrenchment and
how much cultural scaffolding in the
history that led to this condition
limits our ability to make changes on a
large scale you can also see it another
way by looking at a time stamp where if
you see the same location in two
different times here we have a city in
China where over the period of 30 years
the landscape has changed dramatically
as urbanization has set in so the human
population has been growing and the city
went from being very sparsely populated
to very densely populated and there's a
trajectory of scaffolding and
development that has caused this and so
to think of dealing with large-scale
social problems like say global warming
what we need to move away from fossil
fuel infrastructure we can start to
think about how these large-scale
developmental processes and the various
kinds of cultural scaffolding involved
limit our ability to make substantial
changes so this leads to a profound and
somewhat disturbing question or are we
already locked into an unsustainable
future what are the limitations of the
current lock in or entrenchment of our
social infrastructure are we teaching
things to children as they grow up so
that they have the skills and knowledge
and the practices that they need to help
a transition to the sustainable world
and would they be able to survive
through disruptions if we're not able to
also are we able to change things like
the infrastructure for transportation
and energy or agriculture when so much
entrenchment has already happened these
are really important questions and a
good place to start really unpacking
them is with a really seemingly simple
question how much can still be changed
so just as we saw with the development
process across the lifespan for a human
being and we saw across those changing
landscapes of cities and countryside's
that some of the changes are so deeply
entrenched that they be very difficult
to reverse but there are some things
that can be changed so a key question
for us as you ponder what this cultural
scaffolding approach to thinking about
cultural change suggests is that there
gonna be a lot of things that can't be
changed or things that can be changed
will require work and effort to move
away from one developmental pathway to
another and that that can be quite
difficult and time-consuming to do so
how much can still be changed needs to
be answered in two ways one is what can
be changed at all is it even possible to
make a change of a particular kind with
another thing is on the timescales that
we have to address different problems
can we make the changes that are needed
in the time for those problems to be
addressed this is particularly crucial
for global warming where we need to
remove carbon dioxide from the
atmosphere and dramatically change our
land use practices and energy
infrastructure and a time frame that
keeps us safe from runaway global
warming so there are time scales that we
need to think about for those sorts of
problems one way to begin to reflect on
what can be changed is to reflect on
what has already changed and I'm showing
you this image of Africa where you can
see in a very large and dramatic
impression from the
the image that the Sahara Desert is
absolutely huge
this desert covers about a third of the
largest landmass on earth it's it's
gigantic it's almost inconceivable how
big it is but what most people don't
know is that the Sahara Desert has only
been a desert for five or six thousand
years during the last kind of halfway
between the time of the last ice age in
the present day we've had a massive
change in the land use of the African
continent that has happened in
conjunction with changes in planetary
climate to create the largest desert on
earth so one thing that you can think
about here is that the timeframe that it
took to turn this lush green landscape
into that giant desert with several
thousand years so to try to reverse that
and make that giant desert desert lush
and green again well it may not take
several thousand years it certainly
can't be done over a period of three or
four years so you can begin to think
about global scale processes setting
their own constraints on what can and
can't be done in a given timeframe now I
want to share another way of thinking
about cultural scaffolding that really
was not presented originally as cultural
scaffolding but in the context of
thinking about these developmental
processes that limit the patterns that
can emerge in the future just glance at
the different graphs that I'm showing
now and some of them may be difficult to
read because they're small but every one
of these graphs is showing a timeframe
of the industrial era from 1750 to the
present day where you can see there have
been massive changes in things like the
amount of atmospheric carbon dioxide or
the amount of foreign direct investment
in fossil fuels or the growth of the
human population and you can see the
arise and the incurrence rate of great
floods or that you can see there being a
shrinking of global biodiversity as
as an extinction event is taking place a
mass extinction event is beginning to
happen what all these graphs indicate in
their own ways is that there's a huge
amount of momentum in our globalized
economic system and that it's built up
over a period of several hundred years
so the cultural scaffolding that has put
us on a pathway toward ecological
collapse is huge and very substantial so
this calls into question the possibility
of making a transition to sustainability
so now we can ask a question like this
you know which future will we guide
ourselves toward as a species
and what I hope you are really feeling
at this point in the presentation is
that we're limited in the kinds of
changes we can make for our future so
part of our future that we will guide
ourselves is the future we've already
been guiding ourselves toward for
several hundred years because the
cultural scaffolding throughout that
time gave rise to the explosion of human
population and the acceleration of
technology and the use of energy
especially fossil fuels so during the
last 250 years we have seen a
considerable amount of pathway
constraint that tells us quite a lot
about what pathway we are now on so
we've already been guiding ourselves
toward a future that we may not have
been aware of so part of answering this
question is to understand what those
constraints are but another part is to
ask what can still be changed and what
kind of future do we want this is a
challenge for what I call culture design
which is the into the scientific
approach to intentional change at large
skills so this concept of cultural
scaffolding comes from the study of
cultural evolution which is basically to
take an approach similar to how Charles
Darwin thought about changes in species
in biology in this idea of natural
selection that there is an analogous way
of thinking about culture where it's an
evolutionary process where there's a
variety of different cultural traits at
any given time and some of those trained
some of those behaviors ideas practices
etc or more adapted to their
environments than others and so the
better we understand how evolution
informs cultural adaptiveness the better
we can apply cultural scaffolding
processes to social change efforts so we
are going to try to make the change from
our current trajectory to one that gets
us the planetary sustainability we will
have to use culture design to do it and
so right now we hold in our hands the
future of our entire world and so as you
think about what I've said here in this
presentation that cultural scaffolding
is a set of generative interactions
between actors artifacts practices and
infrastructure that the patterns are
constrained in ways that we really need
to understand very well so as we
consider our future together in this
period of time where disruptions are
quite huge in the futures is not looking
that positive for us we really need to
take seriously this cultural scaffolding
process and I want you to know that I
take it very seriously
this is a picture of my ten month old
daughter Elise and I am very
thoughtfully trying along with my wife
we are both but I thoughtfully trying to
develop the cultural scaffolding we feel
she will need in our parenting
philosophies so that we can help her to
thrive as an adult in the middle of the
21st century so just as we are taking
great care to raise our child we feel
that there's need for our societies to
take great care to create the
scaffolding that will create resilience
and thriving for entire communities and
regions of people so as I think about
the future I think of my daughter at
some point being an adult and she's
going to see a world in front of her
that we helped create so this idea of
cultural scaffolding is also very
interesting in that it's ultimately up
to
to choose what kinds of developmental
pathways we want for the future of
humanity and life on earth and the
future that we are choosing today in our
actions and our collective decisions are
going to create the world that our
children will experience tomorrow as
adults and so with that in mind
I really hope to leave with you a sense
of responsiblity the cultural
scaffolding is not just something that
you can let happen accidentally or be
controlled by someone else is taking the
world toward a place that you don't feel
is right for your children that it's up
to all of us to create the cultural
scaffolding that we'll need to get there
with that in mind I just say let's get
to work we have a lot of culture design
that we need to do to build the
scaffolding for our future
onward fellow humans